It's pretty simple. There are nine, sort of, rules
الموضوع في غاية البساطة، هناك تسعة، أنواع ، من القواعد
that I discovered after 35 years of rock climbing.
التي أكتشفتها بعد 35 عاماً من تسلق الجبال.
Most of them are pretty basic.
معظمها أشياء أساسية جداً.
Number one: don't let go --
رقم واحد: لا تستسلم--
very sure success method.
بالتأكيد طريقة ناجحة جداً.
But really, truly -- often you think about
لكن حقيقة، صحيحة-- دائماً تفكّر في
letting go way before your body does.
الإستسلام قبل أن يفعل جسمك ذلك.
So hang in there,
لذا أنتظر هناك،
and you come up with some pretty peculiar solutions.
وستخرج ببعض الحلول الغريبة جداً.
Number two: hesitation is bad.
رقم أثنان: التردد سيئ.
This is a friction climb, up in Tuolumne Meadows,
هذا تسلق لمنحدر، عالياً في تيولومني ميدوزا
in the Yosemite high country.
في يوسيمايت هاي كنتري.
Friction climbing doesn't have any sort of hard positive edges.
ليس لتسلق المنحدرات أي نوع من الحواف الصلبة.
You're climbing on little dimples and nubbins in the rock.
تتسلق على الدمامل والنتوءات الصغيرة في الصخرة.
The most friction you have is when you first put your hand
أكثر الإحتكاكات تحصل عندما تضع يدك أولاً
or your foot on the rock.
أو قدمك على الصخرة.
And then from that point on, you're basically falling.
وبعد ذلك من تلك النقطة، ستسقط.
So momentum is good. Don't stop.
أذاً النشاط جيد. لا تتوقف.
Rule number three: have a plan.
القاعدة الثالثة: أن يكون لديك خطة.
This is a climb called the Naked Edge,
هذا التسلق يسمى الحافة العارية،
in El Dorado Canyon, outside of Boulder.
في دورادو كانيون، خارج بولدر.
This climber is on the last pitch of it.
هذا المتسلق في الجزء الأخير منها.
He's actually right about where I fell.
هو في الواقع قريب من المكان الذي سقطت فيه.
There is about 1,000 feet of air below him.
هناك حوالي 1000 قدم من الهواء تحته.
And all the hard pitches are actually below him.
وكل الحواف الصعبة في الواقع تحته.
Often what happens is
ما يحصل عادة هو
you're planning so hard for like,
أنت تخطط بشدة لمثل،
"How do I get through the hardest part? How do I get through the hardest part?"
"كيف أعبر الجزء الأصعب؟ كيف أعبر الجزء الأصعب؟"
And then what happens?
وبعدها ماذا يحدث؟
You get to the last pitch. It's easy.
تصل الى الحافة الأخيرة. أنه سهل.
And you're completely flamed out. Don't do it.
وتكون أنت ملتهب تماماً. لا تفعلوا ذلك.
You have to plan ahead to get to the top.
لديك خطة أمامك للوصول الى القمة.
But you also can't forget that each individual move
لكنك أيضاً لا يمكن أن تنسى أن أي خطوة مفردة
you have to be able to complete.
لابد أن تقدر على المواصلة.
This is a climb called the Dike Route,
هذا التسلق يسمى بشارع الخندق
on Pywjack Dome, up in the Yosemite high country.
أو قبة بيرات، عالياً في يوسيمايت هاي كنتري.
The interesting thing about this climb is it's not that hard.
الشئ المثير حول هذا التسلق أنه ليس صعباً بشدة.
But if you're the leader on it,
لكن اذا كنت القائد فيه،
at the hardest move, you're looking at about 100 foot fall,
في الخطوة الأصعب، فأنت تنتظر سقطة من حوالي 100 قدم،
onto some low angle slabs.
على بعض الصخور الحادة
So you've got to focus.
لذا يجب عليك التركيز.
You don't want to stop in the middle like
لا تود التوقف في المنتصف مثل
Coleridge's Kubla Kahn.
كوليردج كوبلا خان.
You've got to keep going.
يجب عليك الإستمرار في السير.
Rule number five: know how to rest.
القاعدة رقم خمسة: أعرف كيف تستريح.
It's amazing. The best climbers
أنها مدهشة. أفضل المتسلقين
are the ones that in the most extreme situations
هم الذين في أصعب الأوضاع
can get their bodies into some position
يقدرون على ترتيب أجسادهم على بعض الأوضاع
where they can rest,
حيث يستطيعون الراحة،
regroup, calm themselves, focus,
التجمّع، إراحة أنفسهم، التركيز،
and keep going.
ومواصلة السير.
This is a climb in the Needles, again in California.
هذا التسلق في النيدليس، مجدداً في كاليفورنيا.
Fear really sucks because what it means is
الخوف حقيقةً مشكلة لانه يعني
you're not focusing on what you're doing.
أنك غير مركّز فيما تفعله.
You're focusing on the consequences of
أنت تفكّر في تبعات
failing at what you're doing
الفشل في ما تفعله
because any given move should require
لأن أي خطوة يجب أن تحتاج
all your concentration and thought processes
كل ما تبذله من عمليات التركيز والتفكير
to execute it effectively.
لتنفيذها بكفاءة.
One of the things in climbing is, most people
أحد الأشياء في التسلق هي، معظم الناس
sort of take it straight on. And they follow the most obvious solution.
نوع ما يأخذونه مباشرة. ويتبعون أكثر الحلول وضوحاً.
This is the Devils Tower in Wyoming,
هذا برج ديفيلس في ويمينغ،
which is a columnar basalt formation
الذي هو تشكيل بازلتي عمودي
that most of you probably know from "Close Encounters."
قد يعرفه معظمكم من " وثيقة إنكاوترز."
With this, typically crack climbers
مع هذا، متسلقي الحفر
would put their hands in and their toes in
سيضعون أيديهم داخله وأصابع أقدامهم في الداخل،
and just start climbing.
وبعدها يبدأون التسلق.
The cracks are too small to get your toes into
الحفر صغيرة جداً بالفعل لوضع أصابع القدم داخلها
so the only way to climb is using your fingertips
لذا فالطريقة الوحيدة لتسلقها هي إستخدام حواف الأصابع
in the cracks,
في الحفر،
and using opposing pressure
وإستخدامها لعكس الضغط
and forcing yourself up.
ودفع نفسك لأعلى.
Rule number eight: strength doesn't always equal success.
القاعدة رقم ثمانية: القوة لا تساوي النجاح دائماً.
In the 35 years I've been a climbing guide
في ال 35 سنة التي كنت مرشداً للتسلق
and taught on indoor walls, and stuff like that,
ودرّست في الحوائط الداخلية، وأشياء من هذا القبيل،
the most important thing I've learned
الشئ الأكثر أهمية الذي تعلمته
was, guys will always try to do pull-ups.
كان، يحاول الأشخاص دائماً السحب الى أعلى.
Beginning guys, it's like, they thrash, they thrash,
المبتئدون، أنه مثل ،يضربون، يضربون،
they get 15 feet up --
يصلون الى علو 15 قدماً.
and they can do about 15 pull-ups right --
ويستطيعون فعل حوالي 15 سحب لأعلى صحيح؟
And then they just flame out.
وبعد ذلك يرهقون فقط.
Women are much more in balance
النساء أكثر إتزاناً بكثير
because they don't have that idea
لأنه ليس لديهن تلك الفكرة
that they're going to be able to do 100 pull-ups.
أنه سيكون بمقدورهن فعل 100 سحبه لأعلى.
They think about how to get the weight over their feet
يفكرن حول كيفية جعل الوزن فوق أقدامهن
because it's sort of natural -- they carry you all day long.
لأن ذلك نوع ما طبيعي. يتحملنّ طوال اليوم.
So balance is really critical,
لذا فالإتزان مهم جداً
and keeping your weight on your feet,
والمحافظة على وزنك على قدميك،
which is your strongest muscle.
التي هي أقوى العضلات.
And of course there is rule number nine.
وهناك بالطبع القاعدة رقم تسعة.
I came up with rule number nine after
وصلت الى القاعدة رقم تسعة بعد
I actually didn't plan for a fall,
لم أخطط في الواقع للسقوط،
and went about 40 feet and cracked a rib.
ووصلت لحوالي 40 قدماً وتصدّع أحد الأضلاع.
Once you get to that point where you know it's going to happen,
بمجرد وصولك لتلك النقطة حيث تعرف أنها ستحصل،
you need to start thinking about how you're going to let go
تحتاج للتفكير حول كيف ستسقط
because that is the critical piece
لأن ذلك هو الجزء الحرج
of not getting hurt --
لكي لا تؤذى--
how you're going to fall onto the rope,
كيف ستسقط على الحبل،
or if you're climbing without a rope,
اذا كنت تتسلق بدون حبل،
fall to a place where you can actually control the fall.
أسقط على مكان حيث يمكنك التحكم في السقوط.
So don't hang on till the bitter end.
لذا لا تنتظر حتى النهاية.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)